   For your midterm homework assignment you will creating a “sound board” prototype (with Processing, Beads, ControlP5, and a text-to-speech library) that implements the sound scheme for a modern context-aware version of the Nomadic Radio (NR) project (see below for links to NR papers to use as reference). The goal is not to attempt to recreate the exact NR functionality, but to come up with your own scheme for sonifying communication information modified by context (physical environment, user’s primary task/attentional demands, and the priority/content of the information)
You will create a program that loads in an event stream that represents the types of communication information that we typically receive now on our mobile devices. You will have a user interface that lets the user pick different example contexts (which will control realistic background sounds over which your sonifications will be played), and a series of buttons that let the user personalize the sonification scheme based on their preferences for which information feeds that want to hear. Then the program will sonify the stream in real-time.

The key to this assignment is that your system needs to gracefully sonify all the information feeds in a way that is appropriate given the context. Just like in NR, your system should use a layered approach where depending on environmental background noise, information type, information priority/urgency, and user interruptibility/attentional resources the system chooses how much of the information to convey and whether to use auditory icons, earcons, text-to-speech, and/or filters to modify sound in real-time etc. to do so. Also, at times, there will be multiple pieces of information coming in at once and your system must mix the sound channel together in a way that allows the user to discern all of the channels, but that allots more focus to the information of higher priority. Beyond those requirements, it is up to you to come up with the details of the sonification and mixing approach.

The goal is for the user to be able to listen to this stream of aggregated communication data (in a manner appropriate for the context and without disrupting their primary task) and understand what types of messages are coming in and choose to respond appropriately based on their content.

Event framework and sample data files are attached to this assignment

Information Feeds:

Your system must handle events from these sources with these parameters specified.

Twitter: time stamp, tweet author, tweet text, priority (1-4 where 1 is lowest priority and 4 is highest), number of retweets, number of favorites
Email: time stamp, email sender, email text, priority (1-4 where 1 is lowest priority and 4 is highest), email content summary (1-3 where 1 is positive, 2 neutral, and 3 negative)
Text message: time stamp, text sender, text, priority (1-4 where 1 is lowest priority and 4 is highest), text content summary (1-3 where 1 is positive, 2 neutral, and 3 negative)
Phone call: time stamp, caller (name or phone number), priority (1-4 where 1 is lowest priority and 4 is highest)
Voice Mail: time stamp,  caller (name or phone number), voicemail message as text, priority (1-4 where 1 is lowest priority and 4 is highest), voicemail content summary (1-3 where 1 is positive, 2 neutral, and 3 negative)
The Contexts:

Your system must adapt based on four possible contexts

Working Out: User is running on a treadmill in a gym

     Physical environment: sounds of other’s in the gym, music, the treadmill, of user footsteps and breathing etc.      Moderate level of constant sound.
     Interruptibility: user has plenty of cognitive resources to devote to listening to information

     Social Environments: User isn’t interacting with anyone so it would be appropriate for her to become engrossed in a      message. And she is free to quit her task to attend to communications if she chooses to.

Walking: User is walking across campus to class

     Physical environment: sounds of the outdoor environments, cars driving by, etc. May have moments of loud noise      such as sirens

     Interruptibility: User has some cognitive resources to devote, but for safety reasons she needs to not be so distracted      that she stumbles on a curb, loses her way, or makes an error crossing the street. Also, she needs to hear      environmental sounds for safety reasons and this may affect the volume, length, and number of audio streams your      system plays.

     Social Environments: User isn’t interacting with anyone so it would be appropriate for her to become engrossed in a      message. And she is free to quit her task to attend to communications if she chooses to.

Socializing: User is hanging out with friends at a coffee shop

     Physical environment: sounds of the coffee shop environment, friends talking, user talking occasionally etc. Possibly      quite loud

     Interruptibility: User has some cognitive resources to devote, but she also wants to be able to follow the conversations      happening with her friends

     Social Environments: User is interacting albeit in an informal environment. She may not wish to be distracted so much      that her friends become annoyed with her lack of attention. 

Presenting: User is actively giving a class 

     Physical environment: “your” voice doing a presentation along with sounds like people quietly typing on laptops and      shifting in their seats. Relatively quiet.

     Interruptibility: User is very engrossed with doing her presentation and needs to avoid distraction so she can do a good      job on her talk.

     Social Environments: User is standing up in front of the class. It would be very inappropriate for her to become      distracted by the system. However, she still needs to be aware of very urgent information (e.g. a high priority call from      her mother, a text that her car is being towed) and a low lightweight presentation of less urgent information might be      acceptable (these choices are up to you). 

Requirements: (100 pts total)

1)✅ (7 pts) Four buttons on the UI that let the user choose a context. Each button will trigger a nicely looped clip of realistic background sounds. These background sounds will help a user explore whether your sonification scheme would meld sonically with the environment. The button also controls settings in the code that determine how to present and mix the different communication events based on the environment, interruptibility, and social setting.

2)✅ (5 pts) Check boxes/radio buttons representing the five types of events present in a stream (Twitter, Email, MissedCall, TextMessage, Email). The user can choose which event types she wants to hear/receive. User can turn these on and off in real-time. The number of active event types will affect how your sonification scheme chooses to present and/or mix sounds.

3)✅ (3 pts) There is a button/checkbox that turns a “heartbeat” sound on and off. This is a continuous unobtrusive sound of your own design that indicates the system is working. 

4)✅ (5 pts) Three buttons on the UI that let the user choose which example event stream (JSON) to load (the three example JSON streams will be provided by the instructors). 

5)✅ (10 pts) System does real-time sonification of the data from the event stream

6)✅ (25 pts) System has a dynamic sonification “engine” that chooses which events to sonify, how to sonify them, and how much information from the event to present, based on the current context and the number of active streams as determined by the check boxes. The scheme changes significantly and dynamically based on these factors

7)✅ (5 pts) Your engine must utilize auditory icons and earcons

8)✅ (5 pts) Your engine must synthesize at least one of the sound cues dynamically in code, rather than by playing a premade sound file.

9)✅ (5 pts)You must utilize text-to-speech in some manner in at least one of the context modes.

10)✅ (10 pts) Individual event sonifications are fitting for the event type and context.

11)✅ (10 pts) Groups of simultaneous sonifications (and the “heartbeat” indicator) are mixed appropriately.

12)✅ (10 pts) A design document that explains the reasoning and motivations behind your design choices. Describe how your sonification scheme works for each event type and context. Cite any related work/additional resources you used to inform your design choices.

Deliverables:

1) The Processing application that lets the user explore how the system would respond to different events in different contexts

2) A design document that describes how your version presents the different events in different contexts. Include one or more detailed scenarios  that help illustrate the user experience to the reader and diagrams/tables that describe the layered (see the NR CHI ’99 paper for examples of both). Motivate your design choices.

Extra Credit:

You can receive up to 10 extra points if you implement a feature that allows you to review past events in a relatively short aggregated sonification scheme that the user can access to get an overall sense of what types of information have been received over a previous span of time (For example, the NR project had a mode where messages were spatialize around the user’s head like a clock face and could be scanned quickly to get an overall picture of the information)